Guide to the Ephraim Peter Roberts papers circa 1775-1968
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Ephraim Roberts papers
circa 1775-1968
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 1148
Roberts, Ephraim Peter, 1825-1893
1.75 cubic feet 4 document cases, 1 oversize folder
Papers of a missionary from Vermont and Maine who served in Panape, Micronesia, in the mid-19th century and later settled in The Dalles, Oregon. Includes journals of Roberts and his wife Myra Farrington Roberts, correspondence, family letters, biographical materials and genealogies.
Biographical Note
Ephraim Peter Roberts was born at Danbury, Vermont, October 23, 1825. After completing studies at Williams College in 1854, he entered Bangor Theological Seminary in Maine, and was ordained by the Congregational Church at Bangor on July 28, 1857. On Septermber 8, 1857, he married Myra Holman Farrington of Holden, Maine, born there September 22, 1835. Both having been certified as missionaries by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, they sailed from Boston on October 30, 1857, en route to Micronesia via Cape Horn and Honolulu. Fellow passengers on the Eliza and Ella were the David Dwight Baldwins, also newlyweds, on their way to the American Board mission at Lahaina, Maui.
After a six month voyage to Honolulu, the Roberts stayed there three months until the missionary packet Morning Star was made ready for its second voyage to Micronesia. The ship sailed June 30, 1858, with Ephraim and Myra Roberts, Mrs. Luther Halsey Gulick and three of her children, and Mrs. Gulick's brother-in-law, Theodore W. Gulick. They arrived at Ponape, Caroline Islands, on August 18th.
The Roberts spent the next three years at Shalong, Ponape, replacing Dr. and Mrs. Luther H. Gulick who, with the A. A. Sturges', had established the Ponape mission in 1852. During these years the first two of the Roberts' nine children were born. By mid-summer of 1861 their fellow missionaries to Micronesia decided that the Roberts' should leave Ponape for a number reasons. Two-year-old Charlotte Roberts had somewhat fragile health, and fear for her life was heightened by the death of the Sturges' little girl at Ronkiti, Ponape. Also, whaling vessels were calling less frequently at the islands, life there was increasingly isolated, and mission work was not proceeding as had been hoped. When Mrs. Sturges's health seriously failed, making necessary her return to Honolulu, the Roberts were urged to go too.
They again sailed on the Morning Star, in July of 1861, wound up their American Board affairs in Honolulu, and embarked for San Francisco in September. From there they sailed to Portland, Oregon, and settled for a time at White Salmon, Washington Territory. In 1868 they took up a homestead near The Dalles, Oregon, engaged in sheep raising and fruit growing, and devoted much time to the Congregational Church in that area. Ephraim Roberts died February 6, 1893, and Myra Roberts died February 18, 1912.
The collection consists of correspondence, journals, and genealogical notes on the Roberts and Farrington families. The journals (1857-1961) of Ephraim and Myra Roberts relate to the voyage to Micronesia on the packet Morning Star and to their stay in Ponape. Included are early Farrington family letters, letters received by Ephraim Roberts while at Williams College and Bangor Theological Seminary, letters to the Roberts from their families in Maine and Vermont, and letters from fellow missionaries in the Pacific. Correspondents include: Hiram Bingham, Jr., Elias Bond, Titus Coan, Samuel C. Damon, Edward P. and Sarah Doane, Charlotte C. Dole, Daniel Farrington (Myra's brother in California), Jonathan S. Green, Louisa L. Gulick, Luther Halsey, David B. and Sarah Lyman, George and Nancy A. Pierson, Benjamin G. Snow, A. A. Sturges, Booker T. Washington, and Charles H. Wetmore.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Correspondence, 1775-1968
Series B: Journals and notebooks, 1856-1898
Series C: General files, 1832-1968
The collection is also available on microfilm at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
The collection is open to the public.
Library Accessions 10244, 10337, 10342, 10343, 10357.
Additional materials were added to the collection in 1969.
The "Farrington memorial pamphlets," published in 1880 and 1899, were separated to the book collections of the Oregon Historical Society Research Library and cataloged individually.
Spight, Ruth Stephenson, The story of Ephraim Peter Roberts, 1825-1893, and Myra Farrington Roberts, 1835-1912 [Oakland, Calif., 1970]
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Roberts, Ephraim Peter, 1825-1893--Archives; Roberts, Myra Farrington, 1835-1912--Archives; Bingham, Hiram, 1789-1869--Correspondence; Bond, Elias--Correspondence; Coan, Titus, 1801-1882--Correspondence; Damon, Samuel Chenery, 1815-1885--Correspondence; Doane, Edward P.--Correspondence; Doane, Sarah Wilbur--Correspondence; Dole, Charlotte Close Knapp, 1813-1874--Correspondence; Farrington, Daniel, fl. 1856--Correspondence; Green, Jonathan S. (Jonathan Smith), 1796-1878--Correspondence; Gulick, L. L. (Louisa Lewis), 1830-1894--Correspondence; Halsey, Luther, 1794-1880--Correspondence; Lyman, Sarah Joiner, 1805-1885--Correspondence; Lyman, David B.--Correspondence; Pierson, Nancy A.--Correspondence; Snow, B. G. (Benjamin G.)--Correspondence; Sturges, A. A.--Correspondence; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915--Correspondence; Wetmore, C. H. (Charles Hinckley), 1820-1898--Correspondence
Farrington family; Roberts family
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
Dalles (Or.)--History; Hawaii--History; Maine--History; Pohnpei Island (Micronesia)--History
Missionaries--Hawaii--History; Missionaries--Micronesia--Pohnpei Island--History; Women--Diaries
Missionaries; Oregon
Diaries; Letters (correspondence); Genealogies
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Correspondence, 1775-1968; Series A
  - Transcripts and copies of selected letters, 1856-1859 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letters to Ephraim P. Roberts while at Williams College and Bangor Theological Seminary
    Copies on reel 1 of microfilm
    - 1846-1849 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - 1850-1851 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - 1852 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - 1853 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - 1854 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - 1855 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Letters to Ephraim P. Roberts at Bangor, including letters from the American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions
    - 1856 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - 1857 January-June (Box-folder 1/9)
    - 1857 July-December (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Letters to Ephraim P. Roberts at Ponape, Hawaii, and in the Pacific Northwest
    Copies on reel 4 of microfilm
    Includes letters from Hiram Bingham, Jr., Elias Bond, Titus Coan, Samuel C. Damon, Edward P. and Sarah Doane, Jonathan S. Green, Luther Gulick, Theodore W. Gulick, George B. C. Ingraham, Edward Johnson, David B. Lyman, George Pierson, Lowell Smith, Benjamin G. Snow, A. A. Sturges, and Charles H. Wetmore
    - 1858 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - 1859 January-June (Box-folder 1/12)
    - 1859 July-December (Box-folder 1/13)
    - 1860 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - 1861, 1865; undated (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Family letters written to Ephraim and Myra Roberts while they were in Micronesia, 1857-1861 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Copies on reels 2 and 5 of microfilm
  - Letters to Myra F. Roberts from her brother Daniel Farrington in California, 1856 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Copies on reel 2 of microfilm
  - Letters to Myra F. Roberts from American Board wives, 1857-1861 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Includes letters from Sarah W. Doane, Charlotte C. Dole, Louisa L. Gulick, Sarah G. Lyman, Lucia G. Lyons, and Nancy A. Pierson
    Copies on reels 3 and 4 of microfilm
  - Ephraim Roberts letters to Myra Farrington, 1856-1857 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Myra Farrington letters to Ephraim P. Roberts, 1856-1857 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Journal and letters of Ephraim and Myra Roberts, mostly written at Shalong, Ponape, Caroline Islands, 1858-1861 (Box-folder 2/6-8)
    Copies on reel 3 of microfilm
  - Letters of Ephraim and Myra Roberts, 1857 September-December (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Robert family letters and copies, 1897-1968 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Ephraim Roberts letters to friends and family (except Myra Roberts), circa 1856 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Farrington family letters, Farrington family
    - Family letters, mostly to and from Myra Farrington Roberts, 1841-1866 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Early Farrington family letters, circa 1775-1816 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Later Farrington family letters and other papers, 1865-1881 (Box-folder 2/14)
      Copies on reel 5 of microfilm
  - General letters and papers, including Ephraim Roberts's will, circa 1870-1936 (Box-folder 2/15)
    Includes letter (typed letter, signed) from Booker T. Washington, 1906
  - Envelopes from letters received, circa 1832-1860 (Box-folder 4/1)
- Diaries and notebooks, 1856-1898; Series B
  - Daily memoranda book of Ephraim P. Roberts, 1856 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Ephraim P. Roberts journal, 1857-1859 (Box-folder 3/1)
    Journal, Boston to Honolulu, 1857 October-1858 March, and Honolulu to Micronesia on the Morning Star, 1858 June-August. Included is a list of "vessels at Ponatik, 1858-1859."
    Typescript transcription included. Copies on reels 2 and 3 of microfilm
  - Ephraim Roberts pocket notebook pages, receipts, and floor plan of house in The Dalles, circa 1898; undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Commonplace book of Ephraim and Myra Roberts, circa 1857 (Box-folder 3/3)
    Includes copies of letters sent
- General files, 1832-1968; Series C
  - Myra Farrington Roberts school compositions, circa 1847-1855 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Ephemera and printed matter, 1854-1947 (Box-folder 3/5)
    Includes calling cards, newspaper clippings, obituaries, medical information, materials related to the American Board of Foreign Missions
  - Printed matter, list of names, and Ephraim Roberts's diploma from Williams College, 1854; undated (Box-folder Oversize Folder)
  - Myra Farrington Roberts reminiscences (typescript and manuscript), undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Roberts and Farrington families biographical materials, notes, clippings, 1843-1968 (Box-folder 3/7)
    Eulogy of John Farrington by J.R. Munsell, 1843 October 22
    Genealogical notes, circa 1846-1857
    Farrington genealogy (notebook), 1859
    Speech, with family history, for Farrington reunion, 1878 August 27
    Postcard for Farrington reunion, 1882
    "The story of Ephraim Peter Roberts and Myra Farrington Roberts," compiled by Mrs. Kenneth Roberts Stephenson, 1968
    Information on the ship Morning Star, undated
    Clippings, 1912-1926
    Recipe book, undated
  - Genealogical and biographical materials, 1873-1936 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Roberts and Farrington family genealogies and biographical materials, 1897-1963 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Farrington family tree, undated (Box-folder Oversize folder)
  - Pocket Bible (New Testament) and Daily scripture promise belonging to Ephraim Roberts, 1832-1845; undated (Box-folder 3/10)